# This script runs in the Praat speech analysis program;
# It starts with one Sound object selected.
# The purpose of the script is to find vowel onsets in the Sound,
# using a procedure similar to Cummins & Port 1998 J.Phonetics
# By courtesy of Hugo QuenÃ©, 
# lines starting with # are comment

# make sure that a single sound is selected
aantalselect = numberOfSelected ("Sound")
# obsolete... getnumberofselected aantalselect Sound
if 'aantalselect'!=1
   print Failure: exactly 1 Sound object should be selected!
   printline
else

# peak must be higher than preceding trough by 'delta' in dB, to qualify as peak
# disregard bottom and top 10% of intensity rise, in dB

# Dec.12th filtering adjusted
# comment vowel energy may be emphasised, by filtering with C=1000, B=500 Hz
form Analysis parameters
   comment A vowel is characterised by a peak in the intensity contour.
   comment You can filter the speech first, before the intensity contour is calculated. 
   comment This filtering will enhance the vowel part of the spectrum. 
   boolean filterfirst 1
   comment _
   comment A relevant peak in the intensity contour must exceed 
   comment a minimum intensity level, which is specified as the 
   comment maximum intensity level minus a `threshold`. 
   comment Intensity peaks below this minimum will be ignored. 
   comment A small value (e.g. 2) will ignore most vowel onsets; a large
   comment value (e.g. 18) may yield spurious vowel onsets.  
   positive threshold_(dB) 2
endform
#   comment For determining the midpoint of the rise, the bottom and top parts are ignored.
#   comment This focuses on the central (and often steepest) part of the rise.
#   comment These ignored margins are defined as the bottom and top `margin` of the rise.
#   positive margin_(proportion) 0.20

# obsolete ... getnameofselected geluid1 Sound 1
name1$ = selected$ ("Sound")
# not necessary ... getidofselected geluidid1 Sound 1

# select selected Sound... not necessary... select 'geluidid1'
# copy object name to 'temp' to avoid resampling of original Sound!
Copy... temp

# downsample
## check current Fs before downsampling #
fs = Get sample rate
if fs>11025
  Resample... 11025 1
  Rename... temp
endif

finish = Get finishing time

if filterfirst
	# filter with CF=1000, B=600, hi-freq attentuation, vowel-freq boost
	# sharpen filter to discard more hi-freq components, B=500
	# Filter (one pole)... 1000 500
	# Dec.12th change of filter, for better results
	# 20050111 name of call has changed in Praat 4.2
	# De-emphasize... 50
	# Filter (de-emphasis)... 50
	Filter (one formant)... 1000 500

	# added Dec.12th
	# the filter operation leaves a longer sound, padded with zeroes
	# discard these extra zeroes
	# see manual p.629
	Extract part... 0 'finish' Rectangular 1 1
	# this leaves an extracted sound "*_part"
	Rename... temp
endif

# calculate intensity contour
# minimum F0 is set to long time window, as suggested by PB, to avoid shimmer and AM
# smooth over 80 ms time window, as suggested by Port
# smooth here over 25 ms time window, also smoothing later when taking derivative
framelength = 0.01
# To Intensity... 12.5 'framelength'
# changed for Tiffany's female voice
# To Intensity... 150 'framelength'
# 20050112 HQ
# changed for Frank Wijnen 's male voice, min pitch across words is 74.9 Hz
# but these values yield too smoothed contour
# 20101202 hq adjusted to value 40, was 100, after vowelonset.3b.praat
# 20101202 hq further adjusted to value 60, was 40, because 
# otherwise some early peaks will not be detected because of time smearing
To Intensity... 60 'framelength'
# 20050112 HQ
# higher precision, sinc70, 
# 20101202 interpolation changed back to Cubic
maxint = Get maximum... 0 0 Cubic
t1 = Get time from frame... 1

Down to Matrix
Rename... temp
endtime = Get highest x
ncol = Get number of columns
coldist = Get column distance

# calculate derivative over window of length 2h+1
# Press, Teukolsky, Vetterling & Flannery 1992 "Numerical Recipes in C" par.5.7
# interval length MUST be an odd number of frames -- otherwise timing points are not correct!
h=1
newt1 = 't1'+('h'*'framelength')
ncol = 'ncol'-(2*'h')
# obtain derivative of Intensity matrix here.
# note that frames are NOT aligned between temp and intdot matrices;
# derivative of interval temp[col-h],temp[col+h] corresponds to temp frame 'col'
# but to intdot frame 'col-h' because intdot frames "start later" and end earlier by 'h' frames ;
# hence intdot frame 'col' corresponds to temp frame 'col'+h in time
# so derivative is taken over interval (col+h-h,col+h+h)
Create Matrix... intdot 0 'endtime' 'ncol' 'coldist' 'newt1' 1 1 1 1 1 (Matrix_temp[1,col+'h'+'h']-Matrix_temp[1,col]) / (2*'h'*dx)

# to make the above work, you have to make sure that there is no speech signal
# in the initial and final portions with duration  h*framelength

# convert derivative of Intensity to Sound # hack from PB
To Sound (slice)... 1
Rename... temp_IntDot

# select this Sound
select Sound temp_IntDot
# find positive extrema, maxima, in derivative of Intensity,
# which correspond to steepest rises in Intensity;
# typically occurring just BEFORE vowel activity in oscillogram
To PointProcess (extrema)... Left yes no Sinc70
Rename... temp_rises

select Sound temp_IntDot
# find negative zero-crossings, or falling zero points, in deriv of Int,
# which correspond to peaks in Intensity;
# typically occurring at MAX vowel amplitude in oscillogram
select Sound temp_IntDot
To PointProcess (zeroes)... Left no yes
Rename... temp_peaks

# assume that true vowel onsets actually occur between moment of steepest rise
# and moment of maximum amplitude.
# 'between' is initially defined as 'halfway in time' between the points.

select PointProcess temp_peaks
Copy... temp_onsets
Remove points between... 0 'endtime'

select PointProcess temp_peaks
npeaks = Get number of points
for pindex from 1 to 'npeaks'
	select PointProcess temp_peaks
	ptime = Get time from index... 'pindex'
	select Intensity temp
	pint = Get value at time... 'ptime' Nearest
	# relative peak intensity, local peak relative to threshold relative to maximum
	# relpint = pint - (maxint-threshold)
	if pint > (maxint-threshold)
		select PointProcess temp_rises
		# the following line leads to crashes when detecting metronome beats
		# rindex = Get low index... 'ptime'
		# because the beats may occur immediately in the file
		# the derivative has no positive zerocrossing BEFORE the peak
		# so there is no detectable RISE before the PEAK
		# this leads to rindex=0 which has fatal consequences furtheron.
		# workaround added Dec.11th:
		# use rtime only if rindex>0
		rindex = Get low index... 'ptime'
		if rindex>0
			rtime = Get time from index... 'rindex'
			# onsettime is halfway in time between steepest-rise-moment and peak-moment
			otime = ('rtime'+'ptime')/2
		else
			otime = 'ptime'
		endif # rindex>0
		select PointProcess temp_onsets
		Add point... 'otime'
		# added code Jan.18 to calculate stress score
		# get actual rise value from temp_IntDot
		# select Sound temp_IntDot
		# rise = Get value at time... 'rtime' Cubic
		# peak = pint-(maxint-threshold)
		# printline BINGO: time='otime' peak='peak' rise='rise'
	endif # pint>threshold
endfor # pindex from 1 to npeaks

# cleanup
select Sound temp
# select Sound temp_rsm
plus Intensity temp
plus Matrix temp
plus Matrix intdot
plus Sound temp_IntDot
plus PointProcess temp_rises
plus PointProcess temp_peaks
Remove
select Sound temp
Remove

# 5 lines to remove additional objects
select Sound temp
select Sound temp_filt
Remove
select Sound temp
Remove


# Draw for visual verification, copied 20101202 from vowelonset.v3b.praat
Erase all
Black
Line width... 1
select Sound 'name1$'
Draw... 0 0 0 0 yes Curve
Red
Line width... 3
select PointProcess temp_onsets
Draw... 0 0 no
Black
Line width... 1

# rename final PointProcess to useful name
select PointProcess temp_onsets
Rename... 'name1$'_onsets'threshold'

# was 1 Sound selected ?
endif